Rabinowitch, Eugene I.; Papers ger075
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
- Writings, 1923-1972; 5
  - Writings by Rabinowitch, 1923-1972; 5.1
    - The Dawn of a New Age, Correspondence, 1962 February-1969 May; Undated (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 1)
    - The Dawn of New Age, Reviews, 1963 September-1965; Undated (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 2)
    - "Dogmatismus, Rationalitat und die Demokratie", 1964 December (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 3)
    - "East West Cooperation in Technical and Scientific Aid to Developing-Nations", Undated (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 4)
    - Elementare Einföhrung in die physikalische Statistik, translation by Eugene Rabinowitch, Book Reviews, 1931-1932 (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 5)
    - Elementare Einfuhtutg in die Quantenmekanik, translation by Eugene Rabinowitch, Book Reviews, 1933 November-1935; Undated (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 6)
    - Elementare Einföhrung in die Wellenmekanik, translation by Eugene Rabinowitch, Book Reviews, 1929 July-1934 (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 7)
    - Emerson, Robert, Biography, 1969 March-1970 December; Undated (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 8)
    - Enciclopedia Della Scienza e Della Tecnica, 1964 June-1964 September (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 9)
    - Encyclopedia Britannica, 1947 April-1949 January (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 10)
    - Encyclopedia of Science and Technology, 1957 November-1968 February (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 11)
    - "Eppur si muove"BAS, 1961 January (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 12)
    - "Exit SST", Undated (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 13)
    - An Experience in Listening to the Dead: The Perils of Nationalism, Foreword by Eugene Rabinowitch, 1969 January-1969 August; Undated (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 14)
    - Explaining the Atom, 1953 January-1969 April (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 15)
    - "The Failure of the UNAEC", 1948 October (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 16)
    - "Fateful Decision", Undated (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 17)
    - "Five Years After", editorial BAS, 1951 January (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 18)
    - "Fluorescence of Carotenids", 1969 January-1970 April; Undated (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 19)
    - "The Future of COSWA", 1962 December (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 20)
    - "General Groves Before the McMahon Committee", Undated (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 21)
    - "Genetic Engineering", BAS, 1971 (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 22)
    - "Harrison Brown: A Changed and Changing World"BAS, 1956 October (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 23)
    - "Heroes of Our Time", BAS, 1962 May (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 24)
    - Ice and Fire, Undated (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 25)
    - Ionnaia teorriia by P. Breier. Translated by Eugene Rabinowitch, 1924 (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 26)
    - "The Lessons of a Fateful Month", editorial, BAS, 1967 December (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 27)
    - "The Listener" Rejoinder, 1971 April (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 28)
    - "Measurement of the Fluorescence Life Time of Chlorophyll a in Vivo", 1969 February-1969 May (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 29)
    - "Mechanisms of Excitation Energy Migration Between Pigment Molecules in Biological Systems", Undated (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 30)
    - "Migration of Electronic Energy from Chlorophyll a to Chlorophyll b in Solutions", 1970 (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 31)
    - "Migration of Electronic Energy from Chlorophyll a to Chlorophyll b in Solutions", 1971 (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 32)
    - "Migration of Excitation Energy from Thionine to Methylene Blue in Micelles", 1969 June-1970 February; Undated (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 33)
    - "Military or Civilian Control", Undated (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 34)
    - "Military Security in the Atomic Age", 1946 April (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 35)
    - Minutes to Midnight, 1950 (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 36)
    - Miscellaneous, 1945 September-1972 June; Undated (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 37)
    - "The Mounting Tide of Unreason", BAS, 1971 May (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 38)
    - Nation Article (untitled galley), Undated (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 39)
    - "Eine Neujahrsansprache", translation by Eugene Rabinowitch, 1967 June-1967 August (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 40)
    - New York Times Editorials, 1968 September-1972 January; Undated (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 41)
    - Now It Can Be Told, book review notes, Undated (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 42)
    - One World or None, book review, Undated (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 43)
    - "Photochemical Reduction of Thionine and Other Thiazine Dyes by CO (II) EDTA Complex in a Heterogeneous System", 1970 March-1971 May (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 44)
    - "Photochemical Reduction of Thionine by Cobalt (II) EDTA Complex in Water-Ether Emulsion", October 1969 - February 1970, Undated (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 45)
    - "Photochemistry of Uranyl Compounds", Argonne National Laboratory, 1954 January (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 46)
    - Photochemistry Research Notes, 1963 May-1967 March; Undated (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 47)
    - "The Photogalvanic Effect: Chemical Properties of the Thionine - Iron System", 1940 February (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 48)
    - Photosynthesis, Correspondence, 1940 January-1971 June; Undated (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 49)
    - Photosynthesis, Royalty Statements, 1945 July-1964 December (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 50)
    - Photosynthesis and Energy Migration, Russian Contributions, Undated (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 51)
    - "Photosynthesis and World Needs for Food and Energy", 1965 January (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 52)
    - "Plans for International Control Take Shape"BAS, Undated (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 53)
    - "Polymerization of Dyestuffs in Solution. Thionine and Methylene Blue", 1941 January (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 54)
    - Proposal for the Establishment of an United Nations Council on Scientific Cooperation, Undated (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 55)
    - "Red drop of the Quantum Yield of Fluorescence of Sonicated Chlorella, Anacystis and Porphyridium", 1968 July (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 56)
    - "Responsibility of Scientists in Our Age", Undated (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 57)
    - "Role of Intellectuals in Education", Undated (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 58)
    - Russia's First Atomic Bomb, 1966 October-1966 December; Undated (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 59)
    - "Science and Humanities in Education", 1958 April (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 60)
    - Science and Public Policy Lectures, 1963 (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 61)
    - "Science to the Rescue", Undated (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 62)
    - "Scientific Revolution", Undated (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 63)
    - "The Scientist in Politics", Monmouth College Speech, 1967 January-1967 April (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 64)
    - "Scientists as Citizens", Mellon Institute Speech, Undated (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 65)
    - "The Scientists Examine Their Responsibility", 1959 March (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 66)
    - The Scientists Speak: Biology, 1965 April-1968 April (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 67)
    - "Senate Debate on Atomic Energy Commission"BAS, 1947 (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 68)
    - "Snow's Fourth Lecture", Undated (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 69)
    - "The Social Responsibilities of Scientists in the Atomic Age", Mellon Institute Speech, Undated (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 70)
    - Space Editorial BAS, Undated (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 71)
    - Spectroscopy and Photochemistry of Uranyl Compounds, 1960 October-1968 January (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 72)
    - "Spectroscopy of Uranyl Salts in the Solid State", Argonne National Laboratory, 1953 November (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 73)
    - "The Superbomb: Is There No Choice?", Undated (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 74)
    - "Ten Years After", editorial BAS, 1952 December (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 75)
    - "Test Ban Now", Undated (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 76)
    - "Thoughts for 1970 BAS, 1970 February (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 77)
    - "A Three Part Memorandum", 1945 August (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 78)
    - "The Truman Doctrine and the Bomb.", editorial BAS, 1947 April (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 79)
    - "Two Proposals", Undated (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 80)
    - "UN Atomic Energy Commission", 1947 (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 81)
    - "Uranyl Fluorescence Intensity and Decay", Argonne National Laboratory, 1954 July (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 82)
    - "Vietnam: Politics vs. Geography (Some heretical thoughts)", 1971 October (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 83)
    - "Washington", Undated (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 84)
    - "Which Way to Security - Secrecy or International Control of Atomic Weapons", Undated (Box 5 (5-Writings), Folder 85)
  - Writings By Others, 1946-1971; 5.2
    The Writings by Others files date primarily from 1960 to 1971. The files are arranged alphabetically by author's, name and then by title. The files contain correspondence, drafts of manuscripts, reprints, pamphlets, and radio broadcasts. An attempt was made to include in this-part unpublished manuscripts or material that would not be readily available from other sources. The manuscripts include documents, which Rabinowitch may have collected because of his specific interest in science or international affairs. Or the manuscripts may have been sent to Rabinowitch by the authors for his review and comment. The writings cover a wide range of topics including nuclear energy, disarmament, population control, chemistry, international politics, and scientific education. Of special interest are the scripts of radio broadcasts entitled "The Fifth Horseman". Broadcast in 1946, this Series was designed to educate the American public about the atomic bomb and the results of its use.
    - Alfven et al., M-70 (untitled), Undated (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 1)
    - Artsimovitch, L. A., "Controlled Nuclear Synthesis - The Basis of Energetics of the Distant Future", Undated (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 2)
    - Atomic Scientists News, 1949 July (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 3)
    - Bardeen, John, "Let's Not Overlook Basic Research", 1966 January (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 4)
    - Bardeen, John, "University - Industry Interaction in Solid State Research", 1966 October (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 5)
    - Bondy, Francois, "Europaeishe Demokratie und Angewandtes Weltbuergertum, 1960 June (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 6)
    - Braun, Armand et al., "Approach to the Study of the Legal Problems Raised by the Sciences and Advanced Techniques", 1965 December (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 7)
    - Butler, Warren L., "Absorption of Light by Turbid Materials, Undated (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 8)
    - Clemens, Walter C., Jr., "Sakharov: A Man for Our Times", Undated (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 9)
    - Council for the Study of Mankind, 1963 December-1965 September (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 10)
    - Crosson, Frederick J.Science and Contemporary Society, 1967 (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 11)
    - Cybernation and Man, 1965 Fall (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 12)
    - Dancoff, S. M. and H. Quastler, Untitled, 1950 April (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 13)
    - Doty, Paul, "The Community of Science and the Search for Peace", 1971 April (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 14)
    - Druin, Victor, "Soviet Scientists Propose to Name the New Element 'Joliot'", Undated (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 15)
    - "Energy Transfer with Special Reference to Biological Systems", commentary, Undated (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 16)
    - Feld, B. T., "Reflections on Three Revolutions--or La Chie En-Lit, Oui!", 1968 May (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 17)
    - Frauenfelder, Hans and Peter Stähelin, "Physik in der Schweiz', 1956 November (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 18)
    - Friborg, Göran, "Impact of Impact", 1970 November (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 19)
    - Ghosh, Ashish K., "Energy Transfer in Dye Detergent Micelles", 1970 April-1970 December (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 20)
    - Herter, Christian A., "National Security with Arms Limitation", 1960 February (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 21)
    - Holloman, J. Herbert", Science and Technology and Economic Growth", 1965 January (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 22)
    - Holton, Gerald, "Influences on Einstein's Early Work in Relativity Theory", 1965 August (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 23)
    - Holton, Gerald, "Physics and Culture: Definition of Goals, and Proposals for Science Instruction", 1963 September (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 24)
    - Jack, Homer A., "Still No Non-Proliferation Treaty: The 1966 U. N. General Assembly Debate", 1966 November (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 25)
    - Lamson, Robert W., "National Population Policy--Needs and Requirements", 1971 April (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 26)
    - Lamson, Robert W., "Science Policy Research--A Suggested Structure to Link National Problems, Goals and Means", 1971 February (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 27)
    - Lifton, Robert J., "Bomb Worship", Undated (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 28)
    - Marquis, Arnold, "The Fifth Horseman", 1946 May-1946 July (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 29)
    - Marquis, Arnold, "The Fifth Horseman", 1946 August-1946 September; Undated (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 30)
    - Marquis, Arnold, "Unlimited Hor izons", Undated (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 31)
    - Massey, H. S. W., "The International Control of Atomic Energy", 1948 June (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 32)
    - Melman, Seymour Inspection for Disarmament, 1958 February (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 33)
    - Melman, Seymour Inspection for Disarmament, 1958 February (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 34)
    - Miscellaneous, 1957 January-1965 October (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 35)
    - Morison, Robert S., "Where Is Biology Taking Us", 1966 October (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 36)
    - Osgood, Charles E., "Conservative Words and Radical Sentences in the Semantics of International Politics", 1967 February (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 37)
    - O'Toole, John, "All the King's Horses and All the King's Men", Undated (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 38)
    - Perrin, Francis, 'L' Essential", 1969 April (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 39)
    - Portmann, Adolf, "Colors of Life", Undated (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 40)
    - Sarabhai, Vikram A., "Employment and Development", 1969 December (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 41)
    - Schilpp, Paul A., "Has the Church a Message for Today's Atomic Age-", 1948 April (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 42)
    - Schultz, Theodore W., "The Food Supply Population Growth Quandary", 1970 January (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 43)
    - Scientist and Citizen, 1967 April (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 44)
    - Seeger, Raymond J., "Michael Faraday: His Scientific Insights and Philosophical Outlook, 1965 February (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 45)
    - Seeger, Raymond J., "On Humanistic Aspects of Entropy", 1965 November (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 46)
    - Seeger, Raymond J., "On the Humanisn of Science", 1966 May (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 47)
    - Sherwin, Martin J., "The Atomic Bomb as History", 1969 Winter-1970 (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 48)
    - Shimkin, Demitri B., "Soviet Asia and the Balance of Power in the North Pacific", 1952 June (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 49)
    - Sineshchekov, V. A. et al., "Chlorophyll- a and Carotenid Aggregates and Energy Migration in Monolayers and Thin Films", 1970 August-1971 February; Undated (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 50)
    - Staley, Eugene, "Combinations of Factors and Development Theory", 1966 (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 51)
    - Stewart, B., "Great Issues", 1966 (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 52)
    - Warshauer, Albert D.Key Information in the Medical and Social Sciences, 1970 August (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 53)
    - Wilken, David, "Abstract of Lecture by Mr. Arnold Frutkin...", Undated (Box 6 (5-Writings), Folder 54)
- Photographs, Undated; 6
  This Series consists of seven photographs, including portraits of Eugene Rabinowitch, Anya Rabinowitch& and Victor Rabinowitch. There is also a photograph of a conference Rabinowitch attended at the Institute on Man and Science. The final photograph is of the 1970 Pugwash Conference held at Fontana, Wisconsin. In addition this Series contains three photographic negatives and 148 slides of graphs depicting photosynthesis processes.
  - Photographs, Undated (Box 6 (6-Photographs), Folder 55)
    Rabinowitch, Eugene I. (2 portraits).
    Rabinowitch, Anya (portrait).
    Rabinowitch, Victor (2 portraits).
    Group photograph, including Eugene Rabinowitch, taken at conference held at the Institute on Man and Science, October 31-November 1, 1968.
  - Photographs, Undated (Box 6 (6-Photographs), Folder 56)
    Group photograph of participants at 1970 Pugwash Conference at Fontana, Wisconsin.
    Three negatives of photosynthesis graphs.
    Three containers of 148 slides of photo-synthesis graphs.
- Tape Recordings, 1958, Undated; 7
  This Series consists of nine reels of tape recordings. In addition, there are fourteen tape cassettes which are duplicates of the reel recordings. The tape recordings include four lectures by Rabinowitch on the subject of photosynthesis; an interview of Rabinowitch by Duncan MacDonald; a Rabinowitch lecture concerning communism and the Soviet Union; a debate between Rabinowitch and Morris Liebman; and a Rabinowitch lecture about the effect of the scientific revolution on man and society. The researcher should note that the tape recordings are of very poor quality. Material has been recorded at various speeds on the same tape. Tapes have also been reused, so that a lecture may have background music.
  - Eugene I. Rabinowitch lecture on communism and the Soviet Union, Undated; 1 cassette (Box 6 (7-Tape Recordings), Cassette 1)
  - Eugene I. Rabinowitch lecture on the effect of the scientific revolution on man and society, Undated; 1 cassette (Box 6 (7-Tape Recordings), Cassette 2)
  - Eugene I. Rabinowitch and Morris Liebman debate sponsored by the Peace Association of America, Undated; 1 cassette (Box 6 (7-Tape Recordings), Cassette 3)
  - Duncan MacDonald interview of Eugene I. Rabinowitch on station WQXR, 1966 August 19; 1 cassette (Box 6 (7-Tape Recordings), Cassette 4)
  - Eugene I. Rabinowitch lecture on photosynthesis, 1958 June 30 (Box 6 (7-Tape Recordings), Cassette 5)
  - 3 cassettes, Undated (Box 6 (7-Tape Recordings), Cassette 6)
  - Eugene I. Rabinowitch lecture on chloroplasts in photosynthesis, 1958 July 1; 2 cassettes (Box 6 (7-Tape Recordings), Cassette 7)
  - Eugene I. Rabinowitch lecture on chlorophyll as an oxidation reduction catalyst in photosynthesis, 1958 July 7; 2 cassettes (Box 6 (7-Tape Recordings), Cassette 8)
  - Eugene I. Rabinowitch lecture on the absorption spectrum in photosynthesis, 1958 July 8; 3 cassettes (Box 6 (7-Tape Recordings), Cassette 9)